Finding Aid for the Kenneth N. Trueblood Papers LSC.0589
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Talks.
  - KNT remarks at Andrea Rich retirement. (Box 35, Folder 18)
  - Notes for TV program "50 Years Ago Today." (Box 35, Folder 19)
  - Hastings High valedictory speech., 1937 (Box 35, Folder 20)
  - Leeds, Cambridge...talk., 1956 Nov. (Box 24, Folder 19)
  - Young 2250., 1985 Oct. 23 (Box 26, Folder 26)
    U-Matic tape.
- Professional organization files.
  Primarily materials related to Acta Crystallographica, where Trueblood served in an editorial capacity, and the American Crystallographic Association, which Trueblood co-founded. Materials include administrative papers, notes and correspondence regarding articles for publication, programs and abstracts, as well as plans and records from symposia.
  - Coeditor of Acta Cryst. I. Correspondence with editor(s). (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - American Crystallographic Association (Administration)., 1960-1962; 1974-1977; 1980; 1990; 1993-1994 (Box 20, Folder 11-13)
  - ACA: Society for the Preservation of Anisotropic Displacement Parameters., 1984-1985 (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - ACA: Patterson Award background. (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - ACA: Patterson Award., 1990 (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - ACA: Buerger Award., 1994, 1997 (Box 20, Folder 17)
  - Burgi-Dunitz I. (Box 22, Folder 19-20)
  - Burgi-Dunitz II. (Box 22, Folder 21-22)
  - ACA programs and abstracts. (Box 28, Folder 1-15, Box 27, Folder 15-34)
  - International Congress of Crystallography programs and abstracts. (Box 28, Folder 16-19)
  - Fourth European Crystallographic Meeting programme and abstracts. (Box 28, Folder 20-22)
  - International Union of Crystallography programmes and abstracts. (Box 29, Folder 1-2, 9-15, Box 28, Folder 23-30)
  - Pittsburgh Diffraction Conference program and abstracts. (Box 28, Folder 31)
  - Crystallographic Society Meeting abstracts. (Box 28, Folder 32)
  - American Society for X-Ray and Electronic Diffraction program and abstracts. (Box 28, Folder 33)
  - Mineralogical Society of America abstracts. (Box 28, Folder 34)
  - 40th Anniversary of the First American Papers in X-Ray Crystallography program. (Box 28, Folder 35)
  - Symposium on Molecular Structure and Spectroscopy abstracts. (Box 28, Folder 36)
  - 7th International Symposium on the Reactivity of Solids programme. (Box 28, Folder 37)
  - Conference on Aging and Achievement paper. (Box 28, Folder 38)
    Trueblood was one of the scientists in this study entitled, Career Patterns of Scientists. Materials also include his handwritten notes on George Orwell's essay, "Politics and the English Language."
  - University of California All-University Faculty Conference programs. (Box 28, Folder 39-40)
  - Proceedings of the Cruickshank Symposium. (Box 29, Folder 3)
    Journal of Molecular Structure includes Trueblood's "Vibrational Parameters in Crystals: Rigid and Non-Rigid Molecules."
  - American Society for X-Ray and Electronic Diffraction membership list. (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Symposium in Honour of J.D. Dunitz program. (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - ACA course for Crystallographers lecture notes. (Box 29, Folder 6-8)
  - [Crystal] structure databases articles. (Box 29, Folder 16)
    Materials include correspondence concerning the presentation of these articles at ACA meetings.
  - International School of Crystallography lecture notes. (Box 29, Folder 17)
  - Crystals and Chemistry Symposium program, speeches and invitations. (Box 29, Folder 18-19)
    Materials concern a weekend of festivities at UCLA in honor of Trueblood.
  - Manufacturing Chemists Association Catalyst Award program. (Box 29, Folder 20)
  - Who's Who and Fulbright Alumni Association directories. (Box 29, Folder 21)
  - [Acta C Papers FG 1279-1282]. (Box 27, Folder 6-7)
  - [Acta C FG 1279, FG 1282, FG 1280, FG 1281]., 1997 (Box 27, Folder 11)
  - CIF files., Ca. 1996 (Box 27, Folder 12-13)
- UCLA Department of Chemistry files.
  Administrative records regarding the Department of Chemistry, where Trueblood served as chair from 1965 to 1970 and from 1990 to 1991. Materials relate to curriculum changes, fundraising, adherence to new laws, teaching assistants, and alumni communication, as well as other departmental duties.
  - Alumni and Alumni newsletter. (Box 19, Folder 18)
  - Alumni newsletters. (Box 19, Folder 19)
  - [Arrowhead Retreat]., 1981, 1986 (Box 19, Folder 20-21)
  - Chem. Dept., 1974-1992 (Box 19, Folder 22-24)
  - Chem. Dept., 1970-1971 (Box 19, Folder 25)
  - Chem. Dept. Critiques., 1956 (Box 19, Folder 26)
  - Chairman's Office., 1970-1990 (Box 19, Folder 27)
  - Graduate Student Rosters, 1966-1997 (Box 19, Folder 28-30)
  - [T.A.'s and incoming graduate student rosters]. (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Seminar announcements, Chem 11C schedule., 1994 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Selmayr Crystal Structure Models in Room 1032., 1955 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Safety. (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Weinstein Chair/DJC., 1985 Apr. 26-27 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - TCH Schedules. (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Advise., 1988-1989 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - UCLA Campaign., 1983-1987 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Waivers "Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974." (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - UCLA grade distribution and Chem 11A results., 1958-1962; 1976-1992 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Chem preliminary exam. (Box 27, Folder 3-4)
  - Information on new curriculum., 1957; 1986 (Box 26, Folder 21)
  - 1st and 2nd year courses committee., 1984-1985 (Box 26, Folder 24-25)
  - Physical-Inorganic-Analytical Group (P-I-A)., 1985-1997 (Box 26, Folder 23)
- Grant applications.
  Grant applications, research proposals, and correspondence regarding grants. Materials include biographical information and publication lists for Trueblood's collaborators.
  - Grant Policies and Procedures. (Box 20, Folder 18)
  - NSF: "Intramol. Dynamics in Cryst" 86-15702, 1987-1989 (Box 20, Folder 19)
  - Application proposal 86-15702. (Box 20, Folder 20)
  - NSF scientific., 1987-1989 (Box 20, Folder 21)
  - Reprints to be sent to NSF. (Box 20, Folder 22)
  - Academic Senate research grant., 1987-1988 (Box 20, Folder 23)
  - Computer Charge Numbers application. (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - University research grant. (Box 29, Folder 22)
    Materials concern UCLA grant application for "Studies of Molecular Structure."
  - NSF grants. (Box 29, Folder 23-28, Box 30, Folder 3-11)
    Box 29: Grant proposals for "Structural Studies of Chiral Complexes and Related Species" and "Structures of and Energy Calculations for Host-Guest Complexes."
    Box 30: Grant proposals and reports for "Structures of and Energy Calculations for Host-Guest Complexes and Spheranes," "Diffraction Studies of Organic Crystals" and "Intramolecular Dynamics in Crystals."
  - X-Ray Studies of Unusual Organic Compounds. (Box 30, Folder 1-2)
    Final Report to Air Force Office of Scientific Research (AFOSR).
  - Research proposal - NSF: Diffraction studies of organic compounds., 1972 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - KNT Grant Requests. (Box 25, Folder 22)
- Research files.
  Materials include Trueblood's research materials such as lab notebooks, notes, calculations, correspondence, manuals, and articles.
  - N-alkyl-N-vinylsulfonamides., 1958-1959 (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - H-Bonds and related., 1950-1995 (Box 21, Folder 17-20)
  - Day's hindered base., 1981-1982 (Box 21, Folder 21)
  - Naphthalene: Diiodotetrafluorobenzene., 1981 (Box 21, Folder 22)
  - Diffractometer use., 1979-1988 (Box 21, Folder 23)
  - Derivative sharpening for Patterson's. (Box 21, Folder 24)
  - T-butylcubylcubane., 1988-1990 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Twinning. (Box 22, Folder 2-3)
  - Atomic scattering factors. (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Models. (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Peak Centers...Peak Heights., 1953, 1959 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous - X-ray, X-tals. (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Back shifts...Fouriers, etc. (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - Methods, analyses - crystal structure. (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - Biographies., Ca. 1950-1996 (Box 22, Folder 14-15)
  - Lightner Bilirubins. (Box 22, Folder 16)
  - Allinger. (Box 22, Folder 18)
  - Crown Ethers and related I. Dunitz. (Box 22, Folder 23)
  - Crown Ethers and related II. (Box 22, Folder 24)
  - Truter et al. Crowns. (Box 22, Folder 24)
  - Crowns and Reld. (Box 22, Folder 25-26)
  - Crowns and Rel'd 2 (Box 22, Folder 27-28)
  - IBM punched card manuals. (Box 31, Folder 1)
    Materials include Trueblood's notes on various types of accounting machines.
  - THM Dat. (Box 31, Folder 2-8)
  - THMA and notes. (Box 31, Folder 9-17)
  - Ibadan and related. (Box 31, Folder 18-19)
  - U.S.S.R. notes. (Box 31, Folder 20-23)
  - Lab notebooks. (Box 31, Folder 24-30)
  - [Correspondence]. (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - HAC0: Free. (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - HAC 2. (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - [Notes]. (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Spherand communication to JACS. (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - [Modified Hemispherands...]. (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Coupled structures. (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Acidity in solids. (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - Bastiansen et al. (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - Bartell, L.S. and related. (Box 32, Folder 10)
  - Catalysis. (Box 32, Folder 11)
  - C.L. Coulter. (Box 32, Folder 12)
  - D.H. Cromer, A. Larson, et al. (Box 32, Folder 13)
  - D. Curtin, I. Paul. (Box 32, Folder 14)
  - V. Dashevsky. (Box 32, Folder 15)
  - Domenicano, Vaciago, et al. (Box 32, Folder 16)
  - Dunitz book. (Box 32, Folder 17)
  - Electron diffraction, microwaves. (Box 32, Folder 18)
  - Interstellar molecules and related. (Box 32, Folder 19)
  - Jeffrey. (Box 32, Folder 20)
  - Kitajgorodskij, A.I. (Box 32, Folder 21)
  - Kollman. (Box 32, Folder 22)
  - M. Laing. (Box 32, Folder 23)
  - Liquid crystals (references). (Box 32, Folder 24)
  - Liquids and solutions. (Box 32, Folder 25)
  - K. Lonsdale et al. (Box 32, Folder 26)
  - Luzzati. (Box 32, Folder 27)
  - Mol dynamics. (Box 32, Folder 28)
  - E. Shefter. (Box 32, Folder 29)
  - Sickle cell anemia. (Box 32, Folder 30)
  - Solid solutions of d l compounds. (Box 32, Folder 31)
  - Stezowski, J. (Box 32, Folder 32)
  - Sheng (sarcophinone). (Box 32, Folder 33)
  - Johnson, Carroll K. (Box 32, Folder 34)
  - Ermer re: C6H6 and related. (Box 32, Folder 35)
  - Notes, clippings, correspondence. (Box 32, Folder 36-39)
  - ST 97. (Box 33, Folder 1-14)
    Correspondence, calculations and research articles shared between Trueblood and Verner Schomaker concerning their publication, "Correlation of Internal Torsional Motion with Overall Molecular Motion in Crystals." This was Trueblood's last major publication.
  - THMB/THMBIM things to be done. (Box 33, Folder 15)
  - ADP tutorial. (Box 33, Folder 16)
  - Normal mode analysis from atomic mean square displacement amplitudes. (Box 33, Folder 17)
  - Atomic displacement parameters. (Box 33, Folder 18)
  - Relation between observed torsional amplitudes... (Box 33, Folder 19)
  - Non metallic metals. (Box 33, Folder 20)
  - THM basic lit. (Box 33, Folder 21)
  - THMA. (Box 33, Folder 22-25, Box 34, Folder 1-9)
  - THMV 6. (Box 33, Folder 26)
  - HBB. (Box 33, Folder 27)
  - CRYPB PUBF (Box 33, Folder 28-29)
  - Standard cryst file. (Box 33, Folder 30)
  - Letters from KNT to EFM. (Box 33, Folder 31)
  - Bond lengths. (Box 33, Folder 32)
  - Pauling, Linus. (Box 33, Folder 33)
  - Dorothy Hodgkin and Linus Pauling tribute. (Box 33, Folder 34)
  - Struchkov, Yuri. (Box 33, Folder 35)
  - TLS. (Box 34, Folder 10-23)
  - Crystal structure articles. (Box 34, Folder 24-33)
    These publications were collected by Trueblood.
  - M. C. Etter. (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Fourier transforms, scattering factors, and related topics. (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - B-12., 1956-1957 (Box 24, Folder 20)
  - Calciferol., 1948; 1953-1963 (Box 24, Folder 21)
  - VIT B12 fragment., 1954-1955 (Box 24, Folder 22)
  - B-12 current., 1955-1958 (Box 24, Folder 23)
  - B-12 lit., reports, etc. (Box 24, Folder 24-26)
  - Hexacarboxylic acid [B12]., 1971 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Hexacarboxylic acid [B12]., 1954-1955 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Air dried B-12., 1955-1962 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - D. C. Hodgkin Festschrift., 1977-1985 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Structure Analysis by post and cable., 1953-1955; 1979-1981; 1985 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    Includes photocopied correspondence between Trueblood and Hodgkin. Also includes correspondence regarding "Structural Studies on Molecules of Biological Interest: A Volume in Honour of Dorothy Hodgkin" and correspondence with Maureen Julian.
  - C-H bond length..., 1965; 1990 (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - Cell Parameter Det. for Triclinic Crystal. (Box 25, Folder 10)
  - Ferrocenes. (Box 25, Folder 16)
  - [HMB-TCNE]. (Box 25, Folder 18)
    Includes correspondence to Maverick.
  - Hoffman K2HCBD., 1970-1971 (Box 25, Folder 19)
  - KNT data collections., 1976 May-Jul. (Box 25, Folder 21)
  - KNT state of structures VII., 1978 (Box 25, Folder 23)
  - Research reports. (Box 26, Folder 17)
  - Hetero-Crown. (Box 26, Folder 20)
- Lecture notes and teaching materials.
  Materials include lecture notes, exams, handouts for classes and guest lectures taught by Trueblood as well as notes and annotated texts from Trueblood's undergraduate and graduate school studies, including course materials from a class he took at California Institute of Technology taught by Linus Pauling.
  - 132 lectures., 1961, 1963 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - All "dittoes" for 132., 1963 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - 132 background. (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Forms (Request for Letter of Recommendation). (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Chem 110A lecture notes. (Box 36, Folder 29-31)
  - Chem 11A lecture notes. (Box 36, Folder 32)
  - Chem 11B lecture notes. (Box 36, Folder 33)
  - Chem 1B problem solving guide. (Box 36, Folder 34)
  - Trueblood's Integration of Rational Functions. (Box 36, Folder 35)
  - Physical Chemistry exam. (Box 36, Folder 36)
  - Comments on Atkins' Physical Chemistry. (Box 36, Folder 37)
  - Chem 110A old exams. (Box 36, Folder 38)
  - Dr. McMillan's Chem 234 notes. (Box 36, Folder 39)
  - Direct Methods 221F Lecture for Bob Sweet., 1980 Mar. (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Chem 1A, 3A preliminary exam results., 1959-1960 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Background to research and related. (Box 26, Folder 22)
  - California Institute of Technology notes.
    - Thermodynamics and stat. mech. - Tolman., ca. 1945-1950; 1955 (Box 25, Folder 29-30)
    - Relativity - Tolman. (Box 25, Folder 31-32)
    - Colloid chemistry - Bodger. (Box 25, Folder 33)
    - Statistical mechanics - Kirkwood., 1947-1948; 1963 (Box 25, Folder 34-35)
    - Solid state chemistry - H. Reiss, 1962; Ca. 1969 (Box 25, Folder 36)
    - Macromolecules 232A - B. Zimm., 1961 (Box 25, Folder 37)
    - Chemical bonds - Pauling. (Box 25, Folder 38-39)
    - Atomic physics - Millikan., Ca. 1942 (Box 25, Folder 40)
    - Physics - Kemble - Harvard., 1939. (Box 25, Folder 41)
    - Math Physics., 1943-1944 (Box 25, Folder 42-43)
    - Thermodynamics - Kirkwood, Tunell, Tolman., 1948-1949; 1925-1960 (Box 26, Folder 1-2)
- Photos, awards and memorials.
  Materials include diplomas and certificates from Trueblood's education at Hastings-on-Hudson Public Schools, awards from Harvard and Caltech, photos and memorials.
  - Hastings High Valedictorian certificate. (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Hastings High diploma. (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - John Harvard Scholarship. (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - Manufacturing Chemists Association Award. (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - Caltech fiftieth anniversary doctoral award. (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - [Professional photos]. (Box 38, Folder 6)
  - [Personal photos]. (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - [Party for the Pecksoks photo]. (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - A Brother's Remembrance. (Box 39, Folder 3)
    Alan S. Trueblood's memorial.
  - Memorials. (Box 39, Folder 4-6)
  - Bulletin board items. (Box 39, Folder 7-18)
    Postcards, notes and calculations from Trueblood's office bulletin board. Materials also include additional folders concerning his desires and care for property, C.V., Selective Service System forms, correspondence with Linus Pauling and some high school papers such as his autobiography.